I'd like to introduce you to an emerging area of science,
أود أن أطلعكم على مجال علمي ناشئ،
one that is still speculative but hugely exciting,
والذي مازال قيد التأمل و لكنه مفعم بالإثارة،
and certainly one that's growing very rapidly.
و بالتأكيد فهو ينمو بسرعة قصوى.
Quantum biology asks a very simple question:
يطرح علم أحياء الكم تساؤلاً بسيطاً:
Does quantum mechanics --
هل ميكانيكا الكم--
that weird and wonderful and powerful theory
بهذه الغرابة والدهشة وقوة النظرية
of the subatomic world of atoms and molecules
للعالم دون الذري للذرات والجزئيات
that underpins so much of modern physics and chemistry --
والذي يدعم بقوة الفيزياء الحديثة والكيمياء--
also play a role inside the living cell?
و يلعب دوراً أيضاً داخل الخلية الحية؟
In other words: Are there processes, mechanisms, phenomena
بعبارة أخرى، هل توجد عمليات، وآليات، وظواهر
in living organisms that can only be explained
في الكائنات الحية والتي نستطيع تفسيرها
with a helping hand from quantum mechanics?
بمساعدة ميكانيكا الكم؟
Now, quantum biology isn't new;
حالياً، علم أحياء الكم ليس شيئا جديداً،
it's been around since the early 1930s.
فهو موجود منذ بداية الثلاثينات.
But it's only in the last decade or so that careful experiments --
لكن فقط خلال العقد الماضي أو يزيد حين أظهرت التجارب الدقيقة--
in biochemistry labs, using spectroscopy --
في مختبرات الكيمياء الحيوية باستخدام التحليل الطيفي--
have shown very clear, firm evidence that there are certain specific mechanisms
أظهرت أدلة قاطعة وبوضوح أن هناك آليات محددة
that require quantum mechanics to explain them.
والتي تتطلب ميكانيكا الكم لشرحها.
Quantum biology brings together quantum physicists, biochemists,
علم أحياء الكم يجمع علماء فيزياء الكم والكيمياء الحيوية،
molecular biologists -- it's a very interdisciplinary field.
وعلماء البيولوجيا الجزيئية فهو مجال متعدد التخصصات للغاية.
I come from quantum physics, so I'm a nuclear physicist.
لقد درست فيزياء الكم، لذلك فأنا عالم فيزياء نووية.
I've spent more than three decades
لقد قضيت أكثر من ثلاثة عقود
trying to get my head around quantum mechanics.
محاولاً فهم علم ميكانيكا الكم.
One of the founders of quantum mechanics, Niels Bohr,
أحد مؤسسي ميكانيكا الكم و هو نيلز بور،
said, If you're not astonished by it, then you haven't understood it.
قال: "إذا لم تكن مأخوذاً بها، فأنت لم تفهمها بعد".
So I sort of feel happy that I'm still astonished by it.
لذلك أشعر بالسعادة نوعاً ما لأنها ما زالت تثير دهشتي.
That's a good thing.
و هو شيء رائع.
But it means I study the very smallest structures in the universe --
ولكنه يعني أن أدرس أصغرالمكونات في الكون--
the building blocks of reality.
أي لبنات بناء الواقع.
If we think about the scale of size,
إذا فكرنا بقياس الحجم،
start with an everyday object like the tennis ball,
بدءً بالأشياء اليومية مثل كرة التنس،
and just go down orders of magnitude in size --
و نزولاً بالترتيب إلى الأقل حجماً--
from the eye of a needle down to a cell, down to a bacterium, down to an enzyme --
من فتحة الإبرة، إلى الخلية، وصولاً إلى البكتيريا، وإلى الإنزيم--
you eventually reach the nano-world.
سنصل بالنهاية إلى عالم النانو.
Now, nanotechnology may be a term you've heard of.
الآن، قد يكون مصطلح النانو مألوفاً بالنسبة لكم.
A nanometer is a billionth of a meter.
النانومتر هو جزء من المليار من المتر.
My area is the atomic nucleus, which is the tiny dot inside an atom.
مجال اختصاصي هي نواة الذرة، وهي النقطة متناهية الصغر داخل الذرة.
It's even smaller in scale.
حتى أنها أصغر من حيث الحجم.
This is the domain of quantum mechanics,
هذا هو مجال ميكانيكا الكم،
and physicists and chemists have had a long time
و لقد أمضى الفيزيائيون و الكيمائيون وقتاً طويلاً
to try and get used to it.
لمحاولة الاعتياد على ذلك.
Biologists, on the other hand, have got off lightly, in my view.
من جهة أخرى فلقد ترجل علماء الأحياء، برأيي.
They are very happy with their balls-and-sticks models of molecules.
هم سعداء جداً بكراتهم و عصيهم كنماذج من الجزيئات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The balls are the atoms, the sticks are the bonds between the atoms.
الكرات هي الذرات، أما العصي فتمثل الروابط بين الذرات،
And when they can't build them physically in the lab,
و عندما لا يستطيعون بناءها فيزيائياً في المختبر،
nowadays, they have very powerful computers
فهم في الوقت الحاضر لديهم أجهزة كمبيوتر فعالة جداً
that will simulate a huge molecule.
و التي باستطاعتها محاكاة جزيء ضخم.
This is a protein made up of 100,000 atoms.
هذا بروتين يتكون من 100,000 ذرة.
It doesn't really require much in the way of quantum mechanics to explain it.
إنه حقاً لا يتطلب الكثير للشرح على غرار ميكانيكا الكم.
Quantum mechanics was developed in the 1920s.
تم تطوير ميكانيكا الكم في العشرينيات.
It is a set of beautiful and powerful mathematical rules and ideas
وهي عبارة عن مجموعة رائعة وفعالة من القواعد الرياضية والأفكار
that explain the world of the very small.
والتي تشرح العالم متناهي الصغر.
And it's a world that's very different from our everyday world,
وهو عالم يختلف كلياً عن عالمنا اليومي،
made up of trillions of atoms.
مصنوع من تريليونات الذرات.
It's a world built on probability and chance.
إنه عالم مبني على الاحتمالية والحظ.
It's a fuzzy world.
إنه عالم غامض.
It's a world of phantoms,
عالم من الخيالات،
where particles can also behave like spread-out waves.
حيث يتسنى للجزيئات أيضاً التصرف مثل الموجات المنتشرة.
If we imagine quantum mechanics or quantum physics, then,
إذا تخيلنا ميكانيكا الكم أو فيزياء الكم، فإنه
as the fundamental foundation of reality itself,
كأساس أولي من الواقع نفسه،
then it's not surprising that we say
فإذن ليس من المستغرب أن نقول
quantum physics underpins organic chemistry.
أن فيزياء الكم تدعم الكيمياء العضوية.
After all, it gives us the rules that tell us
الأهم من ذلك أنها تعطينا القواعد التي تخبرنا
how the atoms fit together to make organic molecules.
كيف تتناسب الذرات معاً لصنع الجزيئات العضوية.
Organic chemistry, scaled up in complexity,
وسَّعت الكيمياء العضوية نطاقها في التعقيد،
gives us molecular biology, which of course leads to life itself.
حيث تمدنا بالبيولوجيا الجزيئية والتي بالتأكيد تقود إلى الحياة نفسها.
So in a way, it's sort of not surprising.
إذا بشكل ما، فإن الأمر ليس مستغرباً جداً.
It's almost trivial.
بل هو عادي جداً في الواقع.
You say, "Well, of course life ultimately must depend of quantum mechanics."
قد تقول: "حسناً، لابد للحياة أن تعتمد كلياً على ميكانيكا الكم."
But so does everything else.
و كذلك كل الأِشياء الأخرى.
So does all inanimate matter, made up of trillions of atoms.
كل مادة غير حية، تتكون من تريليونات الذرات.
Ultimately, there's a quantum level
هناك مستوى كمي في نهاية المطاف
where we have to delve into this weirdness.
حيث يتوجب علينا أن نتعمق في هذه الغرابة.
But in everyday life, we can forget about it.
ولكن في الحياة اليومية يمكننا نسيانها.
Because once you put together trillions of atoms,
لأنه بمجرد أن تضع تريليونات الذرات معاً،
that quantum weirdness just dissolves away.
فإن دهشة الكم تتلاشى تماماً.
Quantum biology isn't about this.
علم أحياء الكم لا يدور حول هذا الموضوع.
Quantum biology isn't this obvious.
وهو ليس بهذا الوضوح.
Of course quantum mechanics underpins life at some molecular level.
ميكانيكا الكم بالطبع تدعم الحياة في بعض مستويات الجزيء.
Quantum biology is about looking for the non-trivial --
علم أحياء الكم يبحث عن المهم--
the counterintuitive ideas in quantum mechanics --
الأفكار الحدسية في ميكانيكا الكم--
and to see if they do, indeed, play an important role
ومعرفة ما إذا كانت، فعلاً، تلعب دوراً هاماً
in describing the processes of life.
في وصف عمليات الحياة.
Here is my perfect example of the counterintuitiveness
و هنا مثالي الممتاز لحدسية
of the quantum world.
لعالم الكم.
This is the quantum skier.
هذا هو متزحلق الكم.
He seems to be intact, he seems to be perfectly healthy,
يبدو سليماً، و يبدو أنه في صحة جيدة تماماً،
and yet, he seems to have gone around both sides of that tree at the same time.
و يبدو أنه قد نما على جانبي تلك الشجرة في نفس الوقت.
Well, if you saw tracks like that
حسنا، إذا رأيت مسارات من هذا القبيل
you'd guess it was some sort of stunt, of course.
فستعتقد بالطبع، أنها نوع من معيقات النمو.
But in the quantum world, this happens all the time.
ولكن في عالم الكم هذا شيئ مألوف جداً.
They can do more than one thing at the same time.
و بمقدورها أن تفعل أكثر من شيء واحد في الوقت ذاته.
Particles can behave like spread-out waves.
يمكن للجسيمات أن تتصرف مثل الموجات المنتشرة.
It's almost like magic.
إنها في الأغلب كالسحر.
Physicists and chemists have had nearly a century
لقد أمضى علماء الفيزياء والكيمياء ما يقرب من قرن من الزمان
of trying to get used to this weirdness.
محاولين الإعتياد على هذه الغرابة.
I don't blame the biologists
أنا لا ألوم علماء الأحياء
for not having to or wanting to learn quantum mechanics.
على عدم تعلمهم أو عدم رغبتهم تعلم ميكانيكا الكم.
You see, this weirdness is very delicate;
فكما ترون، هذه الغرابة بالغة الرقة
and we physicists work very hard to maintain it in our labs.
و نحن علماء الفيزياء نسعى جاهدين للحفاظ عليها في مختبراتنا.
We cool our system down to near absolute zero,
نقوم بخفض حرارة النظام إلى الصفر المطلق،
we carry out our experiments in vacuums,
ونجري تجاربنا في الفراغات،
we try and isolate it from any external disturbance.
ونحاول عزلها عن أي اضطراب خارجي.
That's very different from the warm, messy, noisy environment of a living cell.
وذلك يختلف تماماً عن الدفء، والفوضى، والبيئة الصاخبة للخلية الحية.
Biology itself, if you think of molecular biology,
علم الأحياء بذاته، إذا ما كنت تفكر بعلم الأحياء الجزيئي،
seems to have done very well in describing all the processes of life
يبدو أنها أبلت بلاءً حسناً في وصف كل عمليات الحياة
in terms of chemistry -- chemical reactions.
في ما يتعلق بالكيمياء-- التفاعلات الكيميائية،
And these are reductionist, deterministic chemical reactions,
وهي الإختزالية، التفاعلات الكيميائية القطعية،
showing that, essentially, life is made of the same stuff as everything else,
توضح أن الحياة أساساً مبنية من نفس المواد مثل أي شيئ آخر،
and if we can forget about quantum mechanics in the macro world,
وإذا كان بإمكاننا أن نغض الطرف عن ميكانيكا الكم في العالم الكلي،
then we should be able to forget about it in biology, as well.
إذاً يتوجب علينا أن نغض الطرف بالنسبة لعلم الأحياء أيضاً.
Well, one man begged to differ with this idea.
حسناً، رجل واحد رأى أن يختلف مع هذه الفكرة.
Erwin Schrödinger, of Schrödinger's Cat fame,
إروين شرودنغر، صاحب شهرة قط شرودنغر،
was an Austrian physicist.
و هو فيزيائي نمساوي.
He was one of the founders of quantum mechanics in the 1920s.
يعتبر أحد مؤسسي فيزياء الكم في العشرينيات.
In 1944, he wrote a book called "What is Life?"
كتب في عام 1944 كتاباً أسماه "ما هي الحياة؟"
It was tremendously influential.
و فد كان مؤثراً بشكل عظيم.
It influenced Francis Crick and James Watson,
لقد أثَّر على فرانسيس كريك وجيميس واتسون،
the discoverers of the double-helix structure of DNA.
و اللذين اكتشفا بنية الحمض النووي ذو الحلزون المزدوج.
To paraphrase a description in the book, he says:
ليعيد صياغة الوصف في كتابه قائلاً:
At the molecular level, living organisms have a certain order,
عند المستوى الجزيئي، تتمتع الكائنات الحية ببعض النظام،
a structure to them that's very different
حيث يختلف تركيبها
from the random thermodynamic jostling of atoms and molecules
عن التدافع الحراري العشوائي للذرات و الجزيئات
in inanimate matter of the same complexity.
مقارنة بالجمادات غند نفس درجة التعقيد.
In fact, living matter seems to behave in this order, in a structure,
في الحقيقة، الكائنات الحية تميل إلى التصرف حسب هذا الترتيب وهذه البنية
just like inanimate matter cooled down to near absolute zero,
حيث تبرد إلى ما يقارب الصفر المطلق تماماَ كما يحدث مع الجمادات،
where quantum effects play a very important role.
حيث تلعب تأثيرات الكم دوراً مهماً جداً.
There's something special about the structure -- the order --
يوجد شيئ مميز يتعلق بالبنية، وهو الترتيب
inside a living cell.
داخل الخلية الحية.
So, Schrödinger speculated that maybe quantum mechanics plays a role in life.
لذلك، تكهن شرودنغر أن ميكانيكا الكم لربما تلعب دوراً في الحياة.
It's a very speculative, far-reaching idea,
إنها فكرة متضاربة وبعيدة المنال،
and it didn't really go very far.
ولم ينجح الأمر بشكل كبير.
But as I mentioned at the start,
ولكن وكما ذكرت في البداية،
in the last 10 years, there have been experiments emerging,
خلال السنين العشر الماضية، ظهرت تجارب
showing where some of these certain phenomena in biology
توضح أين هذه الظواهر في علم الأحياء
do seem to require quantum mechanics.
تتطلب ميكانيكا الكم.
I want to share with you just a few of the exciting ones.
أود أن أشارككم بعض من هذه التجارب المثيرة.
This is one of the best-known phenomena in the quantum world,
هذه واحدة من أشهر الظواهر في عالم الكم،
quantum tunneling.
وهي نفق الكم.
The box on the left shows the wavelike, spread-out distribution
الصندوق إلى اليسار يظهر التوزيع الإنتشاري الشبيه بالموجة
of a quantum entity -- a particle, like an electron,
للكيان الكمي. جسيم شبيه بالإلكترون،
which is not a little ball bouncing off a wall.
حيث هي ليست بكرة صغيرة ترتد عن الجدار.
It's a wave that has a certain probability of being able to permeate
إنما موجة ذو قابلية محددة للتغلغل
through a solid wall, like a phantom leaping through to the other side.
خلال جدار صلب، مثل الطيف الذي يعبرإلى الجانب الآخر.
You can see a faint smudge of light in the right-hand box.
يمكنكم أن تروا لطخة ضوء خافت في الصندوق إلى اليمين.
Quantum tunneling suggests that a particle can hit an impenetrable barrier,
يشير نفق الكم إلى أن الجسيم يمكن أن يصطدم بحاجز منيع،
and yet somehow, as though by magic,
وبشكل أقرب إلى السحر،
disappear from one side and reappear on the other.
يختفي من جانب ويعاود الظهور من الجانب الآخر.
The nicest way of explaining it is if you want to throw a ball over a wall,
أجمل طريقة لشرج ذلك هي أنه إذا أردت إلقاء كرة عبر الحائط،
you have to give it enough energy to get over the top of the wall.
لابد أن تزودها بالطاقة الكافية لكي تعبر فوق الجدار.
In the quantum world, you don't have to throw it over the wall,
بالنسبة لعالم الكم، فأنت لست بحاجة لجعلها تعبر الجدار،
you can throw it at the wall, and there's a certain non-zero probability
بل يمكنك رميها تجاه الجدار وبوجود قابلية غير صفرية محددة
that it'll disappear on your side, and reappear on the other.
ستختفي من ناحيتك وتعاود الظهور من الجانب الآخر.
This isn't speculation, by the way.
ليس هذا تخميناً بالمناسبة.
We're happy -- well, "happy" is not the right word --
نحن سعيدون، في الحقيقة "سعيد" ليست بالكلمة المناسبة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
we are familiar with this.
نحن معتادون على هذا.
Quantum tunneling takes place all the time;
نفق الكم يحدث على طول الوقت:
in fact, it's the reason our Sun shines.
في الحقيقة، هو السبب في أن الشمس تشرق.
The particles fuse together,
تلتحم الجسيمات مع بعضها البعض،
and the Sun turns hydrogen into helium through quantum tunneling.
ثم تحول الشمس الهيدروجين إلى هيليوم عن طريق نفق الكم.
Back in the 70s and 80s, it was discovered that quantum tunneling also takes place
بالعودة إلى السبعينيات والثمانينات، اكتُشِفَ أن نفق الكم يحدث أيضاً
inside living cells.
داخل الخلايا الحية.
Enzymes, those workhorses of life, the catalysts of chemical reactions --
الإنزيمات، وهم عمال الحياة، ومحفزات التفاعلات الكيميائية
enzymes are biomolecules that speed up chemical reactions in living cells,
هي جزيئات حيوية تسرع التفاعلات الكيميائية داخل الخلايا الحية،
by many, many orders of magnitude.
عن طريق العديد والعديد من أوامر الحجم.
And it's always been a mystery how they do this.
ولطالما كانت طريقة فعل هذا سراً.
Well, it was discovered
حسناً، تم اكتشاف ذلك السر
that one of the tricks that enzymes have evolved to make use of,
تلك واحدة من الخدع التي طورها الإنزيم لكي يستفيد منها،
is by transferring subatomic particles, like electrons and indeed protons,
وذلك عن طريق تحويل الجسيمات دون الذرية مثل الإلكترونات والبروتونات
from one part of a molecule to another via quantum tunneling.
من أحد أطراف الجزيء إلى آخر عبر نفق الكم.
It's efficient, it's fast, it can disappear --
إنه كافِِ وسريع وبمقدوره الاختفاء
a proton can disappear from one place, and reappear on the other.
بمقدور البروتون الإختفاء من مكان ما ومعاودة الظهور في مكان آخر.
Enzymes help this take place.
حيث يساعد الإنزيم على حدوث ذلك.
This is research that's been carried out back in the 80s,
هذا بحث تم إجراؤه في الثمانينات،
particularly by a group in Berkeley, Judith Klinman.
بالتحديد بواسطة فريق من مدينة بيركيلي. جوديث كلينمان.
Other groups in the UK have now also confirmed
أكدت فرق أخرى من المملكة المتحدة
that enzymes really do this.
أن الإنزيم يفعل ذلك حقاً.
Research carried out by my group --
أجري البحث عن طريق فريقي البحثي...
so as I mentioned, I'm a nuclear physicist,
فكما ذكرت، أنا فيزيائي نووي،
but I've realized I've got these tools of using quantum mechanics
ولكني لاحظت أني أمتلك أدوات مثل استخدام ميكانيكا الكم
in atomic nuclei, and so can apply those tools in other areas as well.
في الأنوية الذرية، وكذلك استخدام هذه الأدوات في مناطق أخرى.
One question we asked
لدينا تساؤل
is whether quantum tunneling plays a role in mutations in DNA.
وهو عمّا إذا ما كان نفق الكم يلعب دوراً في تغيرات الحمض النووي.
Again, this is not a new idea; it goes all the way back to the early 60s.
مجدداً، هذه ليست فكرة جديدة، بل هي تعود إلى بواكير الستينيات.
The two strands of DNA, the double-helix structure,
طوقي الحمض النووي، وبنية الحلزون المزدوج،
are held together by rungs; it's like a twisted ladder.
يتم ربطهما معاً عن طريق درجات، هي مثل السلم اللولبي
And those rungs of the ladder are hydrogen bonds --
ودرجات السلم هذه تمثل روابط الهيدروجين
protons, that act as the glue between the two strands.
تعمل البروتونات مثل الغراء فيما بين الطوقين.
So if you zoom in, what they're doing is holding these large molecules --
لذا، إذا ما كبرت الصورة، ستجد أن مهمتهما هي الإمساك بهذه الجزيئات الضخمة
nucleotides -- together.
النيوكليوتيدات معاً.
Zoom in a bit more.
كبر الصورة أكثر.
So, this a computer simulation.
هذه محاكاة عن طريق جهاز الحاسوب.
The two white balls in the middle are protons,
الكرتين البيضاويتين في المنتصف هما عبارة عن بروتون،
and you can see that it's a double hydrogen bond.
وتلاحظون أنها رابطة هايدروجين مزدوجة.
One prefers to sit on one side; the other, on the other side
أحدهما يفضل البقاء في جانب، والآخر على الجانب المقابل
of the two strands of the vertical lines going down, which you can't see.
للطوقين للخطوط الأفقية المتجهة للأسفل، والتي ليس بمقدوركم رؤيتها.
It can happen that these two protons can hop over.
قد يحدث أن يقفز هذين البروتونين.
Watch the two white balls.
انظروا إلى الكرتين البيضاويتين.
They can jump over to the other side.
بمقدورهما القفز إلى الجانب الآخر.
If the two strands of DNA then separate, leading to the process of replication,
في حال انفصال طوقي الحمض النووي، مسبباً ذلك عملية التكرار،
and the two protons are in the wrong positions,
ووجود كلا البروتينين في وضعية خاطئة،
this can lead to a mutation.
قد يقود هذا إلى حالة من التغيّر الإحيائي.
This has been known for half a century.
وهذا أمر معروف منذ نصف قرن.
The question is: How likely are they to do that,
السؤال المفترض: كيف من المرجح أن يحدث ذلك،
and if they do, how do they do it?
وإذا ما حدث، فكيف حدث ذلك؟
Do they jump across, like the ball going over the wall?
هل عبرت من خلاله، مثل الكرة تعبرفوق الحائط؟
Or can they quantum-tunnel across, even if they don't have enough energy?
أو عن طريق عبور نفق الكم، حتى وإن لم تتمتع بالطاقة الكافية؟
Early indications suggest that quantum tunneling can play a role here.
الدلائل الأولية تشير إلى أن نفق الكم قد يلعب دوراً في هذا الأمر.
We still don't know yet how important it is;
وحتى الآن لا ندرك مدى أهمية الأمر:
this is still an open question.
مازال هذا سؤالاً مفتوحاً.
It's speculative,
إنه مدعاة للتأمل،
but it's one of those questions that is so important
ولكنه أحد تلك الأسئلة المهمة جداً
that if quantum mechanics plays a role in mutations,
عما إذا كانت ميكانيكا الكم تلعب دوراً في التغيرات الإحيائية،
surely this must have big implications,
بالتأكيد لابد أن لهذا آثاراً كبيرة،
to understand certain types of mutations,
من أجل فهم أنواع محددة من التغيرات،
possibly even those that lead to turning a cell cancerous.
حتى تلك التي تقود إلى تحول الخلية إلى خلية سرطانية.
Another example of quantum mechanics in biology is quantum coherence,
مثال آخر لميكانيكا الكم في علم الأحياء هو التماسك البيولوجي،
in one of the most important processes in biology,
في واحدة من أهم العمليات في علم الأحياء،
photosynthesis: plants and bacteria taking sunlight,
وهي البناء الضوئي: تستقبل النباتات و البكتريا أشعة الشمس،
and using that energy to create biomass.
مستخدمة تلك الطاقة لخلق الكتلة الحيوية.
Quantum coherence is the idea of quantum entities multitasking.
تماسك الكم هو عبارة عن تعدد مهام كيانات الكم.
It's the quantum skier.
إنه عبارة عن متزحلق الكم.
It's an object that behaves like a wave,
عبارة عن شيئ يتصرف مثل الموجة،
so that it doesn't just move in one direction or the other,
لذلك لا ينحصر الأمر في حركته في اتجاه واحد أو عكسه،
but can follow multiple pathways at the same time.
بل بمقدوره أن يسلك عدة اتجاهات في نفس الوقت.
Some years ago, the world of science was shocked
قبل عدة سنين، تعرض مجتمع العلوم إلى حالة صدمة
when a paper was published showing experimental evidence
عندما تم نشر ورقة تظهر دلائل تجريبية
that quantum coherence takes place inside bacteria,
أن تماسك الكم يحدث في داخل البكتريا،
carrying out photosynthesis.
محدثاً ذلك عملية التمثيل الضوئي.
The idea is that the photon, the particle of light, the sunlight,
الفكرة هي أن الفوتون، وجسيم الضوء، وأشعة الشمس
the quantum of light captured by a chlorophyll molecule,
وكمية الضوء الملتقطة عن طريق جزيء الكلوروفيل،
is then delivered to what's called the reaction center,
يتم تحويلها إلى ما يسمى مركز التفاعل،
where it can be turned into chemical energy.
حيث يتم تحويلها إلى طاقة كيميائية.
And in getting there, it doesn't just follow one route;
وهنا فهي لا تسلك طريقاً واحداً،
it follows multiple pathways at once,
بل تسلك عدة طرق في نفس اللحظة،
to optimize the most efficient way of reaching the reaction center
من أجل الوصول إلى أفضل طريقة لتحقيق مركز التفاعل
without dissipating as waste heat.
دون التشتت كحرارة مبددة.
Quantum coherence taking place inside a living cell.
يحدث تماسك الكم داخل الخلية الحية.
A remarkable idea,
فكرة إستثنائية،
and yet evidence is growing almost weekly, with new papers coming out,
ومازالت الأدلة تتوالى أٍسبوعياً تقريباً، مع خروج أوراق جديدة للعلن،
confirming that this does indeed take place.
مؤكدة أن ذلك يحدث حقيقة.
My third and final example is the most beautiful, wonderful idea.
مثالي الثالث والأخيرهو الفكرة الأجمل والأروع.
It's also still very speculative, but I have to share it with you.
هي مازالت في طور التأمل، ولكن لابد أن أشارككم بها.
The European robin migrates from Scandinavia
يهاجر طائر أبو الحناء من الدول الاسكندنافية
down to the Mediterranean, every autumn,
وصولا الى البحر الأبيض المتوسط، كل خريف،
and like a lot of other marine animals and even insects,
ومثل العديد من الحيوانات البحرية وحتى الحشرات،
they navigate by sensing the Earth's magnetic field.
فهي تستهدي عن طريق الاستشعار بالمجال المغناطيسي للأرض.
Now, the Earth's magnetic field is very, very weak;
الآن، المجال المغناطيسي للأرض يعتبرضعيفاً جداً
it's 100 times weaker than a fridge magnet,
فهو أضعف بمقدار 100 مرة من مغناطيس الثلاجة،
and yet it affects the chemistry -- somehow -- within a living organism.
وعلى الرغم من ذلك فهو يؤثر على الكيمياء داخل الكائن الحي بشكل أو بآخر.
That's not in doubt -- a German couple of ornithologists,
هذا ليس محل شك، فقد أثبت عالما طيور ألمانيين،
Wolfgang and Roswitha Wiltschko, in the 1970s, confirmed that indeed,
وهما وولفغانغ وروسويثا ويلتشوك في السبعينيات تلك الحقيقة،
the robin does find its way by somehow sensing the Earth's magnetic field,
يعرف أبو الحناء طريقه عن طريق استشعار المجال المغناطيسي للأرض،
to give it directional information -- a built-in compass.
مما يمده بمعلومات توجيهية، كما البوصلة.
The puzzle, the mystery was: How does it do it?
وقد كان الغموض في كيفية حدوث ذلك.
Well, the only theory in town --
حسنا، النظرية الوحيدة
we don't know if it's the correct theory, but the only theory in town --
لاندري إن كانت النظرية الصحيحة، ولكنها النظرية الوحيدة المتاحة--
is that it does it via something called quantum entanglement.
أنه يستعين بما يسمى بتشابك الكم.
Inside the robin's retina --
في داخل شبكة عين أبو الحناء--
I kid you not -- inside the robin's retina is a protein called cryptochrome,
أنا لا أمزح، في داخل شبكة عين أبو الحناء يوجد بروتين يسمى بالكربتكروم،
which is light-sensitive.
وهو حساس للضوء.
Within cryptochrome, a pair of electrons are quantum-entangled.
داخل الكربتكروم يوجد زوج من الإلكترونات متشابك كمياً.
Now, quantum entanglement is when two particles are far apart,
الآن، تشابك الكم هو عندما يوجد جسيمين بعيدين من بعضهما البعض،
and yet somehow remain in contact with each other.
ورغم لك، يظلان في حالة اتصال مع بعضهما البعض.
Even Einstein hated this idea;
حتى إنشتين كره هذه الفكرة
he called it "spooky action at a distance."
فقد سماها "تأثير شبحي من على البعد."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So if Einstein doesn't like it, then we can all be uncomfortable with it.
لذا في حال أن إنشتين لم يحبها،فيمكننا أن نكون غير مرتاحين لهذا الأمر.
Two quantum-entangled electrons within a single molecule
إلكترونان في حالة تشابك كمي داخل جزيء واحد
dance a delicate dance
يرقصان رقصة رقيقة
that is very sensitive to the direction the bird flies
ذلك أمر حساس جداً لاتجاه تحرك الطيور
in the Earth's magnetic field.
داخل المجال المغناطيسي للأرض.
We don't know if it's the correct explanation,
لا ندري إن كان ذلك هو التفسير الصحيح،
but wow, wouldn't it be exciting if quantum mechanics helps birds navigate?
ولكن، أليس شيئاً مثيراً إن كانت ميكانيكا الكم هي ما يساعد الطيور على النتقل؟
Quantum biology is still in it infancy.
مازال علم أحياء الكم في مراحله الأولى.
It's still speculative.
مازال الأمر مدعاة للتفكير.
But I believe it's built on solid science.
ولكني أؤمن أنه بني على قواعد علمية صلبة.
I also think that in the coming decade or so,
أعتقد أيضاً أنه خلال السنوات العشر القادمة أو نحو ذلك،
we're going to start to see that actually, it pervades life --
سنشهد ذلك على أرض الواقع، وسيعم الأمر حياتنا
that life has evolved tricks that utilize the quantum world.
وأن الحياة طورت خدعاً تنتفع من عالم الكم.
Watch this space.
شاهدوا هذا الفضاء
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)